Matthew Schultz

Baltimore, MD • Phone: 410-375-8667

Email: matt@matthewkschultz.com • Website: https://www.matthewkschultz.com

Summary

I have a passion for creativity, problem-solving, and service that has motivated me throughout my career as an Team Lead and Principal Application Engineer as well as with my prior experience in team management, partnership building, consensus building, facilitation, education, and applied social sciences.

Abilities

Languages (Programing): Javascript, HTML, CCS, SQL, Java

Frameworks/Libraries: React, Ionic Capacitor, Fabric, Leaflet, AngularJS, Jest, SQLite, SCSS, JQuery

Design: Mobile-first Design, Responsive Design, User Interface Design, Privacy by Design

Social: Team Leadership & Mentoring, Experiential Learning Facilitation, Inter-Agency Conference Facilitation, Community Building & Engagement, Intergroup Dialogue, Conflict Resolution, Consensus Building, Theatre of the Oppressed, Nonprofit Management, Youth Education

Languages (Human): English (Native), Spanish (Fluent)

Work Experience

Team Lead/Principal Application Engineer, <u>Youreka Labs</u> Web/Mobile Engineer, <u>Synaptic AP</u>, Annapolis, MD

2021-08-11 to Present 2016-02-15 to 2021-08-11

A founding engineer on an enterprise-level smart forms application that scaled into its own company that was later purchased. More than 30,000 Youreka forms are created daily for onsite inspections, maintenance, compliance, and auditing. I am currently overseeing a team of 6 engineers balancing the refactor of both the mobile and web apps from older technologies while also adding new features requested by customers. Our app was part of Synaptic AP and was then spun off into its own company that was purchased by Dispatch.

- Architect: Lead team collaboration to design, engineer, and write technical requirements for new features in a way that integrates the joint knowledge, experience, and requirements of the team and clients. This includes customer feedback, user testing, adoption metrics, and market trends as part of a team including data analysts, graphic designers, sales people, marketing staff, and other engineers.
- **Project Management:** Run stand-ups, sprints, and ensure team meets release deadlines. Manage iOS App Store and Android Play Store listings and mobile app releases.
- **Leadership:** Supervise and mentor engineers on coding, design, architecture, testing, and documentation base practices.
- **Client Support:** Educate clients on app functionality and assist with their implementation issues.
- Primary Technologies: Javascript, React, Zustand, Ionic Capacitor, SQLite, Jest, Android Studio, Xcode, AngularJS, JQuery, HTML and CSS.

Experiential Learning & Dialogue Facilitator

2009-11-05 to Present

Freelance, Baltimore, MD

- **Team Collaboration Skills:** Interactive trainings allowing participants to collaborate in new ways, look at problems from different perspectives, and build a more integrative collaborative practice as a team.
- **Team Retreats: Appreciation, Purpose, and Action:** Team Building activities retreats to build a shared vision of purpose, mutual appreciation, and action.

Architect / Product Owner / Co-Founder

2013-08-01 to 2018-06-12

SocietyLab

Created a start-up with a partner for a social media platform that leveraged data visualization for collecting, exploring, and sharing information and ideas in a way that respects privacy and breaks users' filter bubbles.

- Architect & Engineer: Created full stack web application with users, login, database, and a dynamic UI for adding, collecting, and exploring collections of links using data visualization.
- Product Designer: Integrated academic literature, industry advocates, user feedback, and personal experience to design an user experience for users to create and share collections of information.
- Primary Technologies: Javascript, Node, Angular, D3, Mongo, Mongoose, AWS

MS Access & MS SharePoint Engineer / Project Manager / Facilitator

Centers for Medicare & Medicaid Services, US Gov't, Woodlawn, MD 2015-05-04 to 2016-02-12 2013-01-07 to 2015-04-30 ERP International/HCD International, Woodlawn, MD

Worked initially as a contractor and then federal employee for the Center for Program Integrity in the Centers for Medicare & Medicaid Services combating Medicare fraud, waste, and abuse.

- Systems Engineer and Administrator: Engineered and implemented a database interfaced to track information and create automated reports on session logistics, participants, action items, and feedback and evaluation forms for the Command Center and the CPI Governance Council.
- Facilitator: Facilitated high-level inter- and intra-agency sessions bringing together policy experts, data analysts, law enforcement, and investigators from various agencies in remote and in-person settings.
- Primary Technologies: Microsoft Access, Microsoft Sharepoint, HTML and CSS.

Program Manager - Youth

2009-03-04 to 2013-01-06

International Rescue Committee, Baltimore, MD

Led a comprehensive Family Support and Wellbeing program for resettled refugee youth in the Greater Baltimore area.

- **Program Developer and Scaler:** Developed a comprehensive Family Support & Wellbeing program consisting of caseworkers providing life skills trainings for parents and youth, contracted mental health therapists providing support groups, and technical assistance and partnership building with teachers, school leadership, and area hospitals.
- Partnership Builder: Developed organizational partnerships and sat on advisory boards for the Johns Hopkins Bayview Mental Health Clinic, the Maryland Board of Education, Baltimore City Schools, and the Metropolitan Association of Foreign Student Advisers.
- Data Analyst: Worked with staff to develop a rubric to monitor client wellbeing. Used the rubric data to identify issues and trends with clients using statistical methods with the R programming language.
- **Supervisor:** Supervised staff, contracted therapists, interns and volunteers.
- Grants and Budget Manager: Successfully wrote and managed private and federal grants. Managed the program budget.

Program Manager

2005-06-01 to 2009-09-24

Kids for Peace, Baltimore, MD

A summer camp, yearly youth summits, and a year-round youth leadership program teaching about world cultures and issues of peace, justice, and conflict resolution

- Curriculum Developer: Create age-appropriates lessons on complex issues such as child soldiers or the Darfur conflict for elementary and middle school students.
- **Supervisor:** Managed the logistics of a summer camp and several youth summits about specific conflict.
- Web Master: Created and updated the organization's website with program information and photos from recent events using HTML and CSS.

Education

American University, School of International Service

05/2010

International Peace and Conflict Resolution, Masters of Arts Concentration: Conflict Resolution and Dialogue Facilitation

Thesis: Implementing Legal Pluralism in Oruro, Bolivia

05/2005 **Towson University**

Jazz/Commercial Music Composition, Bachelor of Music Degree (Minor in Spanish)